A Finding Aid to the Philip Stein Papers Regarding David Alfaro Siqueiros, 1933-2012, in the Archives of American Art AAA.steiphil
Archives of American Art
Philip Stein papers regarding David Alfaro Siqueiros
1933-2012
AAA.steiphil
Archives of American Art
3.7 Linear feet
The papers of muralist, writer, and activist Philip Stein regarding the Mexican muralist David Alfaro Siqueiros measure 3.7 linear feet and date from 1933 to 2012. The papers reflect Stein's relationship with Siqueiros as an art assistant and their shared commitment to leftist politics. Much of the material relates to Stein's book Siqueiros, His Life and Work (1994) and his first book The Mexican Murals (1984). Found are research materials, correspondence, interviews, printed material, photographic materials, video and film recordings, writings about and by David Alfaro Siqueiros, and materials concerning Stein as a painter.
Stein, Philip, 1919-2009
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The Philip Stein papers regarding David Alfaro Siqueiros were donated to the Archives of American Art in 2015 by Anne Stein, daughter of Philip Stein.
Conditions Governing Access note
Use of original material requires an appointment and is limited to the Archives' Washington, D.C. Research Center. Use of archival audiovisual recordings with no duplicate access copy requires advance notice.
Biographical/Historical note
Artist, author and political activist, Philip Stein (1919-2009), also called "Estano," lived and worked in New York City, Mexico, and Spain. Stein worked as an assistant to muralist David Alfaro Siqueiros. Both men were committed to the Mexican Mural School of new-realism, painting exterior murals rather than easel paintings so art could be public and directed to the masses.
Stein was born in Newark, New Jersey and was a mostly self-taught artist, occasionally studying at local art schools. He served in the armed forces during World War II as a meteorologist, seeing action throughout Europe. After the war, he moved to California to paint movie sets. In 1948, Stein and his wife Gertrude moved to Mexico where he studied art on the GI Bill at The School of Fine Arts of San Miguel de Allende. There he met Siqueiros, an ardent communist, who had attempted to assasinate Leon Trotsky. Stein worked with Siqueiros on several murals in Mexico until Siqueiros' death in 1974.
Between 1953 and 1993 Stein occasionally exhibited in Mexico, New York City and Spain. One of Stein's best known murals is at the Village Vanguard club in New York City. His biography of Siqueiros, Siqueiros, His Life and Work was published in 1994. Stein died at home in Manhattan in 2009 at age 90.
Scope and Contents note
The papers of muralist, writer, and activist Philip Stein regarding the Mexican muralist David Alfaro Siqueiros measure 3.7 linear feet and date from 1933 to 2012. The papers reflect Stein's relationship with Siqueiros as an art assistant and their shared commitment to leftist politics. Much of the material relates to Stein's book Siqueiros, His Life and Work (1994) and his first book The Mexican Murals (1984). Found are research materials, correspondence, interviews, printed material, photographic materials, video and film recordings, writings about and by David Alfaro Siqueiros, and materials concerning Stein as a painter.
Arrangement note
The collection is arranged in 7 series:
Series 1: Correspondence, 1934-2010 (0.3 linear feet; Box 1)
Series 2: Interviews, 1977-1994 (0.1 linear feet; Box 1)
Series 3: Writings, 1937-2006 (0.6 linear feet; Boxes 1-2)
Series 4: Subject Files and Research Files, 1933-2009 (0.6 linear feet;Boxes 2-3)
Series 5: Printed Material, 1949-2009 (0.7 linear feet; Boxes 2-3,5)
Series 6: Photographic Materials, 1933-2005 ( 0.5 linear Feet; Boxes 3-4)
Series 7: Sound, Video and Film Recorings, circa 1967-2012 (0.9 linear feet; Box 3)
- Correspondence, 1934-2010; Series 1; 0.3 Linear feet Box 1
  Scope and Contents note
  Philip Stein's correspondence is both professional and personal in nature. Diana Zykovsky Anhalt wrote about American expatriates in Mexico during the McCarthy era and Stein was concerned with the accuracy of Anhalt's representation of his activities. Correspondence with Angelica Arenal de Siqueiros, and Adriana and Robert Siqueiros is mostly in Spanish, and relates to Stein's research for Siqueiros, His Life and Work. Correspondence with Graciela de Arenal, also in Spanish, is of a personal nature. The Raphael Cruz Arvea correspondence involves the translation of Stein's book. David Siqueiros' correspondence include letters from the Communist Party and a photocopy of a letter from Diego Rivera.
  - Diana Zykovsky Anhalt, 1995-2006 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Angelica Arenal de Siqueiros, 1963-1990 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Graciela de Arenal, 1977-2004 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Raphael Cruz Arvea, 1998-2007 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Adriana Siqueiros, 1989-1995 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - David Alfaro Siqueiros, 1934-1953 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Robert Siqueiros, 2005 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Philip Stein, 1955-2010 (Box 1, Folder 8-9)
- Interviews, 1977-1994; Series 2; 0.1 Linear feet Box 1
  Included in this series are casette recordings of an interview with Adriana Siqueiros, Siqueiros' daughter, conducted by Charles Keller and Stanley Faulkner and four interviews with Angelica Siqueiros, his wife.
  - Adriana Siqueiros, 1994; 1 Sound cassettes (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Angelica Siqueiros, 1977-1980; 4 Sound cassettes (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Writings, 1937-2006; Series 3; 0.6 Linear feet Boxes 1-2
  Writings by Stein, Siqueiros and others are in English and Spanish and include audiovisual materials. The materials concern Siqueiros' view of the development of public art in Mexico and the relation between Mexican muralism and the Mexican Revolution. There are speeches by Siqueiros given to the Instituto Nacional de Bellas Artes in Mexico and the Central University of Caracus (Venezuela). Writings by Siqueiros largely concern his position on "his assault of the house of Leon Trotsky" and mass mailing letters regarding his relase from prison in 1964. Found are Stein's notes, four notebooks (with occasional drawings), two journals, jottings, and "final drafts" relating to Siqueiros.
  - Jorge Hernandez Vazquez, "Siqueiros y Su Relacion con los Pintores del Cono Sur," Thesis, UNAM 2006, 1996-2006; 1 Electronic discs (CD) (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Mayer Sasson, Programa Aniversario Siqueiros", New School, 1996; 1 Videocassettes (VHS) (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - David Siqueiros, Speeches, circa 1950 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - David Siqueiros, Writings, 1937-1960 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Philip Stein (Box 1)
    - Philip Stein, Journals, 1973-1980 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - "David Alfaro Siqueiros, Tal y Como Lo Conoci,", after 1958 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Miscellaneous Writings, 1953-1956 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - "Perspective Notes", circa 1940s-circa 1950s (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Notebook, Research re: Mexico, Siqueiros, and Mural Painting, circa 1960s- circa 1970s (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Notes, circa 1950s- circa 1980s (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - "Philip Stein, Siqueiros I, First Draft", before 1994 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - "Philip Stein, Siqueiros II, Second Draft", before 1994 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Talk on Siqueiros, 1994; 1 Sound cassettes (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Writings by Others, Miscellaneous, circa 1951-2003 (Box 2, Folder 1-2)
- Subject Files and Research Files, 1933-2009; Series 4; 0.6 Linear feet Boxes 2-3
  Files include materials relating to Philip Stein's exhibitions, as well as materials concerning Diego Rivera and Jackson Pollock. There are FBI files for both Stein and Siqueiros. Also found are articles by Hugo Gellert and a transcript of an interview with him, and items by scholar, Larry Hulburt and Mark Vallen, artist-activist. In addition to sketches by Stein, there are clippings relating to the Hollywood Strike of 1946, clippings and material concerning the "assault on Leon Trotsky," and notes and clippings covering the 1960 Siqueiros trial. Further, there are materials regarding Stein's book The Mexican Murals (1984), correspondence and commentary on Siqueiros, His Life and Work (1994) and materials from the 1996 symposium on Siqueiros, "Otras Rutas Hacia Siqueiros."
  - Luis Arenal, 1933-1980s (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - FBI Files on David Alfaro Siqueiros (photocopies), 1943-1965 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - FBI Files on Philip Stein (photocopies), circa 1980 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - "Free Siqueiros" Materials, 1961-1964 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Freedom of Information Act Research, 1984-1997; 1930 (Box 2, Folder 7-8)
  - Hugo Gellert, 1967-1998 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Hollywood Strike, 1990; 1945-1947 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Larry Hulburt, 1974-1977 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Jackson Pollock, 1981-2002 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Polyforum Cultural Siqueiros, 1960s-1970s (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Diego Rivera, 1948-1998 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - San Miguel de Allende, 1948-1949; 1996-2006 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Symposium, "Otros Rutas Hacia Siqueiros", 1995-1996; 1979 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Siqueiros Book, 1955-2009 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Siqueiros Trial, 1960-1968 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Philip Stein, 1953-2005 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Philip Stein, "The Mexican Murals", 1979-2005 (Box 2, Folder 20, Folder 19)
  - Leon Trotsky Assassination Attempt, 1994-1996 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Mark Vallen/Art-For-A-Change, 2003-2007 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Vietnam Anti-War Activities, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - White Chapel Exhibition, Siqueiros, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 24)
- Printed Material, 1939-2009; Series 5; 0.7 Linear feet Boxes 2-3, 5
  Printed material includes a folder of political fliers from the early 1950s, some signed by the "Frente de Pintores Revolucionarios de Mexico" and more recent announcements of events relating to Siqueiros and political action. Found are articles in Spanish by Siqueiros from the newspaper, Excelsior, and articles by othrs relating to muralism and general political developments. There also are exhibition announcements, catalogs and price lists relating to Siqueiros' artwork. Lastly, there is a collection of Mexican periodicals with articles pertaining to Siqueiros' life and work.
  - Book Excerpts about Siqueiros, 1970s-1980s (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Clippings, 1950-2005 (Box 2, Folder 26-27)
  - Clippings, Siqueiros, 1950-2007 (Box 2, Folder 28-29)
  - Conference Announcement and Fliers, 1953-2007 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Excelsior Newspaper Articles by Siqueiros, 1949-1950 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Exhibition Catalogs and Announcements, 1950-2009 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Exhibition Catalogs, Announcements, and Price Lists, Siqueiros, 1962-2004 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Miscellaneous Printed Items, 2008 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Periodicals, 1961-2006 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - "Planeta Siqueiros de JOSE RAMON Mikelajauregui", 1995; 1 videocassette (VHS) (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Oversized Miscellaneous Periodicals (from Box 3, Folder 6), 1939-1970 (Box 5, Folder 1)
- Photographic Material, 1933-2005; Series 6; 0.5 Linear feet Boxes 3-5
  Many of the photographs of Siqueiros, Stein, and others identify those present with notes in English. Siqueiros is shown with his artwork, with his grandfather, with Stein, and at events. There are both portraits of Siqueiros and Angelica Renal de Siqueiros and digital prints of Stein with family or friends. Also found are numerous photographs and slides of Siqueiros' and Steins' artwork.
  - "Angelica" and Artwork Slides, 1960s-1970s (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Artwork by Siqueiros and Stein, 1933-2001; 19 slides; includes slides; oversized material housed in Box 3, Folder 9 (Box 3, Folder 9-11)
  - Mural Book, 1962-1979 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Places, 1966-1968 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Robert and Cristella Siqueiros, "Photos w/ Gertrude and Philip Stein", 2005; 1 Electronic discs (CD) (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Siqueiros, Stein and Others, 1927-circa 2000 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Slides of Siqueiros' Murals, Easel Paintings, and Miscellaneous Artwork, circa 1960s-circa 2000 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Oversized Artwork Siqueiros and Stein (from Box 3, Folder 9), 1933-2001 (Box 5, Folder 2)
- Sound, Video, and Film Recordings, circa 1967-2012; Series 7; 0.9 Linear feet Box 3-4
  The sound and video recordings appear to include documentary presentations.
  - "Mexico Siqueiros" and "Murals 74 and 77 Mexico", 1973-1977; 1 Film reels (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - "Legacy & Legend Siqueiros, Siqueiros & Americal Tropical Censorship Defied"' "PBS Siqueiros", 2010-2012; 2 Electronic discs (DVD) (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - "Mexican Murals"; "Sp War Murals"; "Mex Arqueolist", 1 Videocassettes (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - "Philip Stein on Siqueiros", 2005; 3 Electronic discs (DVD) (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Unidentified Films, 1972-1975; 2 Film reels (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Unidentified Sound Recordings, 1967-1976; 6 Sound cassettes (Box 4, Folder 1-2)